"Choosing the Best Greens to
Boost GLP-1 for Weight Loss"
In my last video,
I showed how starting your day
with a single dose of thylakoids
increased
feelings of satiety
and decreased hunger and
cravings for snacks and sweets
throughout the day.
We’re talking about
a powdered spinach extract
equivalent to just half a cup
(80 g) of cooked greens.
Significantly less desire
for salty snacks
over the next nine hours
compared to placebo,
with just one dose of greens.
Significantly less desire
for sweet snacks, sweet and fat,
snacks in general.
Thylakoids, thus,
provide a powerful strategy
to suppress the urge
for so-called "palatable" food,
potato chips, chocolate,
cinnamon buns, and the like.
But despite the lower hunger
and greater satiety,
food intake throughout the day
was not significantly affected.
In a systematic review
of randomized clinical trials
on the effects
of thylakoid intake
on appetite and weight loss,
the hunger-suppressing effects
of thylakoids
were reported
in all the relevant studies,
but what about
the weight-loss part?
Instead of a single dose
of greens,
what about the same dose
every day for three months?
The title gives it away:
you get a loss of body weight,
reduced cravings,
and increased release
of the appetite-suppressing
hormone GLP-1.
The average amount
of weight loss
was only about three pounds
(1 kg),
but the study participants
also got
a significant drop
in cholesterol of 20 points,
and, as you can see,
the drop in cholesterol preceded
significant weight loss;
so, the cholesterol benefit
wasn’t just because
weight was being lost.
And 20 points?
That’s the kind
of result you get
using an earlier class
of cholesterol-lowering drugs.
GLP-1 was also boosted by about
40 percent, and check this out:
significantly lower
cravings for sweets
even 11 hours
after spinach intake.
And, remember,
the spinach powder was hidden;
so, people didn’t know
which group they were in,
didn’t know if they were getting
greens or placebo.
And 11 hours later,
they were, like, chocolate?
Eh, no thanks.
Uh, got any spinach?
So, not only were there
decreased cravings
in the six hours
prior to lunch,
but also decreased cravings
afterwards--
all from just getting
that one single dose of greens
in the morning.
That’s the power of GLP-1.
Now, one of the authors
had a conflict of interest,
affiliations with companies
trying to commercialize
thylakoid products,
and you can see it in the spin.
They described
the spinach extract
as markedly
reducing body weight,
but I wouldn’t consider
three pounds (1 kg) "markedly."
They boast that
the 6 percent weight loss
was comparable to an older GLP-1
drug available at the time,
suggesting that increasing
the natural release of GLP-1
may be as efficient
as pharmacological agents
for the treatment for obesity.
Of course, our new GLP-1 drugs
can decrease body weight
by more than 6 percent,
but the 6 percent loss
in this study
was from baseline,
not compared to placebo.
Those on the placebo lost about
4 percent of their body weight;
so, weight loss
attributable to the spinach
was more like only 2 percent.
And another eight-week study
found no significant difference
at all.
So, when they took
their supplement
to the European equivalent
of the U.S. Food and Drug
Administration
to try to make
a weight-loss health claim,
the panel was, like,
a 1 percent weight loss?
That’s really not going
to do much.
Whether these appetite-lowering
effects of thylakoids
could be a useful strategy
in controlling obesity
in the long term
is still ambiguous.
More studies are needed.
And, here we go, the latest
thylakoid weight loss study.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
with that same dose
equivalent to half a cup (80 g)
of cooked greens,
and there was a significant
decrease in body weight,
fat mass, waist circumference,
waist-to-height ratio,
and body mass index (BMI)
compared to placebo--
and, by a decent amount.
Individuals in the spinach group
lost 15 pounds (7 kg),
compared to 7
in the placebo group.
Eight more pounds (3 kg)
of weight loss on greens
than placebo.
And that included
8 pounds of straight fat,
including 4 more centimeters
off the waist.
So, based on a systematic review
of the potential effects
of thylakoids
in the management of obesity,
eating green can suppress
hunger, reduce food intake,
and result in weight loss.
Greens can offer a means
to strengthen our resolve
to refrain from eating,
especially when we’re in a kind
of high-doughnut environment
where there is
"superfluous access
to foods processed
to deliver qualities
that some may find
irresistible."
It’s interesting,
even supplementing a breakfast
that was only 11 percent fat
with thylakoids resulted in
decreased hunger and cravings,
suggesting that there
might be other mechanisms
for the appetite-suppressive
effect of thylakoids
beyond just slowing
the digestion of fat.
Here are some of the proposed
mechanisms aside from GLP-1
that may be contributing
to weight loss.
Regardless, what’s the best way
to get them?
Not from the supplement aisle,
but rather the produce aisle.
And remember, that’s where
the chlorophyll is found;
so, you can see
with your own eyes
which veggies
have more thylakoids
by how dark green they are.
What happens
when you cook greens?
Blanched for 15 seconds or so
in steaming or boiling water,
they actually get
even brighter green,
but if you cook them too long,
they eventually turn
a drab olive brown.
When greens are overcooked,
their thylakoids
physically degrade,
along with their ability
to slow fat absorption.
Within that first minute
of cooking,
when the green gets
even more vibrant, though,
there’s a slight boost
in fat-blocking ability.
So, you can gauge
thylakoid activity
in both the grocery store
and in your kitchen
with your own two eyes.
We have been chewing on leaves
for millions of years,
but today,
the greenest thing
about some people’s diets
may be a St. Patty’s Day pint.
Americans have averaged fewer
than two grams of spinach a day,
not even half a teaspoon.
But our bodies were designed
to have thylakoids
passing through our systems
on a daily basis;
so, that delay in fat absorption
we get from them
can be thought of
as our default, normal state.
It’s only when we eat diets
deficient in greens
that we suffer
the accelerated fat digestion
that undercuts
our natural satiety mechanisms.
In the journal of the Society
of Chemical Industry,
a group of food technologists
argued that,
given their
fat-blocking benefits,
"thylakoid membranes
could be incorporated
in functional foods
as a new promising
appetite-reducing ingredient,"
or you can just get them
the way Mother Nature intended.